Finding Aid for the June Wayne Papers LSC.0562
UCLA Library Special Collections
June Wayne papers
1909-2012
UCLA Library Special Collections
Wayne, June
LSC.0562
114.0 linear feet (228 document boxes, 10 oversize boxes, and 25 boxes of audiovisual materials)
June Claire Wayne was born on March 7, 1918 in Chicago, Illinois, where at the age of 15 she dropped out of high school to pursue her career as an artist. In addition to her work in lithography, which revitalized the art of printmaking in America, Wayne is well-known for her tapestries and visual explorations of optics and scientific themes. The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, ephemera, and photographs related to the creation and exhibition of Wayne's work, including the production of The Dorothy Series lithographs and film about the artist, Matsumi (Mike) Kanemitsu, Four Stones for Kanemitsu.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page. Boxes 49-103 are closed until the year 2015.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital and audiovisual materials. Digital and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of June Wayne, 2000, 2011, 2012.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9946631193606533
Biography
Visual artist June Claire Wayne was born on March 7, 1918 in Chicago, Illinois, where she was raised by her divorced mother, Dorothy Alice Kline. At age 15, Wayne dropped out of high school to pursue a career as an artist. She had her first solo exhibition under the name of June Claire in Chicago only two years later, followed in 1936 by a second exhibition at the Palacio de Bellas Artes in Mexico City. By 1938 she was already on the WPA Easel Project in Chicago and had achieved prominence among world-famous writers, actors, artists, and scientists in an international milieu in which Wayne is still active.
Around 1939, Wayne moved to New York, where she worked as a costume jewelry designer while continuing to paint at night and on weekends. In the 1940s, she began to work under the name of June Claire Wayne. After Pearl Harbor, she moved to Los Angeles and became certified in production illustration, intending to work in the aircraft industry. However, when she was offered a job in radio writing at WGN in Chicago, Wayne seized this opportunity instead, scripting several programs a day and honing a literary talent that would later produce influential essays on art criticism, artists' rights, and feminism.
When WWII ended, Wayne left Chicago to settle in Los Angeles, where she became an integral part of the California art scene. Inspired by her training in production illustration, Wayne began to produce seminal works of optical art, including The Tunnel and the Kafka series, in the mid 1940s. She continued to expand her artistic horizons, taking up lithography at Lynton Kistler's facility in 1947. Ten years later, she began collaborating with master printer Marcel Durassier in Paris. In their groundbreaking work on the John Donne suite, Wayne invented many of lithography's current techniques, vastly expanding the aesthetic potential of the medium. In order to restore the art of lithography in the United States, she founded the Tamarind Lithography Workshop with the support of the Ford Foundation in 1960. Now known as the Tamarind Institute of the University of New Mexico, this organization continues to thrive and help artists become free enterprise workers in the print world.
Wayne began designing large-scale tapestries in France in 1970, once again embracing a new mode of artistic expression. In this and many other media, Wayne explored avant-garde connections between science, art, and contemporary issues. Motifs as varied as optics, the genetic code, stellar winds, magnetic fields, tsunamis, and temblors figure in her work as complex metaphors for the human condition.
Wayne's art is represented in many museum collections in the USA and abroad, and she has received dozens of awards as well as honorary doctorates in recognition of her innovative and prolific contributions to her artistic fields.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of June Wayne's personal and professional correspondence and documents pertaining to her career as a painter, lithographer, weaver, writer and political and civil activist. Different aspects of her career are highlighted, e.g. her relationship with the Ford Foundation and the Tamarind Lithography Workshop; the process of working on the Dorothy series and the John Donne's book lithographs; events such as exhibits and trips; the filming of the movie, Four Stones For Kanemitsu, that later resulted in litigation; participation in radio and TV broadcasts, such as You and Modern Art; and her involvement in the feminist art movement, e.g. the creation of the Joan of Art seminar series, as well as politics and art when lobbying for better legislation for artists.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Correspondence
Court Cases (Restricted)
Dorothy's Possessions
Employment Reports
Four Stones for Kanemitsu
June Wayne's Events
Press and Publications
Tamarind Lithography Workshop
Photographs
Audiovisual Materials
Slides
Artwork Photographs
Writings and Public Speaking
Arrangement follows original order of collection.
Items Removed from the Collection
Rand McNally Guide to Chicago and Environs (Chicago: Rand McNally, 1924), catalogued and added to general library collection.
Related Material
June Wayne Oral History Transcript, interviewed by Kathryn Smith, [1976]. Los Angeles: Oral History Program, University of California, Los Angeles, c1982.
Interview of June Wayne (2011)
Tamarind Institute Records (Collection MSS 574 BC). Available at the University of New Mexico Center for Southwest Research & Special Collections.
The Dorothy Series: an Audiovisual Biography. DVD.
Lithographers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Audiovisual materials.; Photographs.; Women artists -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Tamarind Lithography Workshop.; Wayne, June, 1918- --Archives.; Wayne, June
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1942-1997
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes Wayne's correspondence with friends, family members, politicians, and colleagues in the field of print making. Topics include Wayne's philosophies on artists' rights, women's rights, and Wayne's creative work. This series is organized into thirteen subseries.
  - Subseries 1: Business, 1942-1999
    This subseries includes Wayne's correspondence regarding various exhibitions of her work in the United States, Australia and Japan, the establishment of the Tamarind Lithography Workshop, the "June Wayne" television series broadcast on KCET, and her activities in the Women In Business and Women's Caucus for Art organizations. Also included are documents regarding Wayne's biographical entries in the Who's Who publications, Wayne's Honorary Doctor of Fine Arts degree from the Rhode Island School of Design, and correspondence regarding Wayne's concerns for the National Endowment for the Arts and artists' rights.
    Organization and Arrangement
    After "Shedletsky, Stuart," additional folders have been arranged alphabetically
    - Lowry, MacNeil Correspondence (Ford Foundation), 1959-1964, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Correspondents include: W. McNeil Lowry (Director, Program in Humanities and the Arts, Ford Foundation) re: establishment of Tamarind Lithography Workshop; Adja Junkers re Wayne's exhibition at Los Angeles County Museum of Art (LACMA); Clinton Adams (head of the Department of Art, University of Florida, Gainesville) re LACMA catalogue; Wayne's written proposal, "Tamarind Lithography Workshop, Inc.: Project prepared for the Program in Humanities and the Arts of the Ford Foundation"; list of names to whom Lowry submitted Wayne's proposal for review and their responses, which include Josef Albers, Garo Z. Antreasian, Will Barnet, Vernon L. Bobbitt, Adelyn D. Breeskin, Lamar Dodd, Ebria Feinblatt, Ernest Freed, Gustave von Groschwitz, Theodore J.H. Gusten, Bartlett Hayes, Arthur W. Heintzelman, Harold Joachim, Una E. Johnson, Jules Langsner, A. Hyatt Mayor, Andrew C. Ritchie, Lessing Rosenwald, Henry J. Seldis, Ben Shahn, Benton Spruance, Frederick S. Wight, and Carl Zigrosser.
    - Hicks, Price (KCET), 1970-1975, 1978, 1980, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Price Hicks (producer, KCET) re taping arrangements for Wayne's "Speculation: A Conversation with June Wayne"; Wayne's request to Hicks re purchasing copies of the "June Wayne" series; "June Wayne" television series summary; guest lists; introductions; Dorothy Kemps (director, KCET Volunteer Center) re Wayne's Achievement Award speech at YWCA Leadership Luncheon (1983.)
    - Kubasik, Ben (Public Relations), 1968-1974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Wayne's views re role of the National Citizens Committee for Public Television; press release re committee receiving grant from Benton Foundation; Wayne utilizes Ben Kubasik and his newly established communications/public relations firm; invitation to party and preview of Wayne's television series, "June Wayne"; tape of Wayne's talk at College Art Association meeting; Kubasik to Otis Chandler re Wayne's exhibition at the Los Angeles Municipal Art Gallery.
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Linda Daita (Adult Education Coordinator, Public Education Department, Whitney Museum of American Art) re request for Wayne's participation in their 1990-1991 seminar series, "Seminars with Artists."
    - Maison Odoul & Co., 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Shipping documents for Wayne's exhibition at La Demeure, Paris ("June Wayne: An Exhibition of Paintings, Tapestries, Lithographs, Los Angeles Municipal Art Gallery, Barnsdall Park, 1973 November 1-December 2, and La Demeure, Paris, 1974 December 1-31.)
    - Publisher Group West; Pucciani, Oreste, 1985, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Kathleen Kennedy (advertising, Publishers Group West Inc.) re including Wayne's work in Fall 1990 catalogue; Publishers Group West Spring 1990 Audio catalogue; Oreste F. Pucciani re Scholarship Fund evening and Special Tribute Award to Rudi Gernreich by the Council of Fashion Designers of American (New York, 1986 January 19); Wayne's paper at conference, The Avant-garde in Literature, Hofstra University (Long Island, 1985 November.)
    - Smith, Benjamin 1969-86, 1969, 1974, 1976, 1979-1981, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Benjamin B. and Dorothy Smith re valuations of Wayne's prints and gifting their Tamarind Lithography Collection to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C.; 1976 valuation of Wayne's painting, "Sanctified"; J. Carter Brown (Director, National Gallery of Art), Andrew Robinson (Curator of Graphic Arts, National Gallery of Art) and U.S. Senator Alan Cranston re gift of Tamarind prints.
    - Rancho Santiago College, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Gene Isaacson (Gallery Director, Rancho Santiago College Art Gallery, Santa Ana, CA) and Tobey C. Moss Gallery re including Wayne's work in exhibition, "New California Painting: Dealer's Choice" (1986 February 24-March 20); exhibition reviews by Suvan Greer (Orange County Register) and John Hamilton (staff writer, Rancho Santiago College student newspaper.)
    - International College, 1974-1975, 1978, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Independent Study Program materials, International College (Los Angeles, CA); Barbara Kibbe re use of Wayne's mailing list and invitation for Wayne to act as tutor.
    - Morrison, Rita (Bequest of "The Advocate"), 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Last Will and Testament of Rita J. Morrison (1989 March 17); correspondents include: Michael J. Fasman and City National Bank (co-executors), Peggy Ornelas (Vice President and Senior Trust Officer, City National Bank), and Burt Levitch, Rosenfeld, Meyer & Susman (attorneys) re distribution of Rita J. Morrison estate; proceeds from the sale of Wayne's painting, "The Advocate."
    - Public Corporation For Arts, Long Beach, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Correspondents include: Harriet Williams (chair, Public Corporation for the Arts, Long Beach, CA) re Wayne's lecture, "The Artists' World--Inside and Outside the Studio" presented (1991 April 30) as part of their 1991 Lecture Series.
    - Inlander, Gail, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Gal Achtenberg Inlander (Flood Gallery, San Francisco) re acting as agent for Wayne's prints and tapestries.
    - Daquin, Pierre, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Pierre Daquin (artist) re contract problems with Arras Gallery (New York); Wayne offers legal assistance of Joseph Rothman through the Artist's Equity union of New York; "Free Unicorn..." exhibition catalogue of Daquin tapestry show at Arras (New York, 1971.)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Art Express), 1981 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Art Express (Kenneth S. Friedman, editor) re advisory board, law suit filed by publisher, Bruce Helander, and Wayne's request to remove her name from the magazine's masthead.
    - American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Letter re request for inactive status in AFTRA.
    - Artists Equity Association of Los Angeles (AEA), 1981 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      AEA (Bill Lasarow, Vice President) re fundraising activities and protocols; letter of recommendation for CCA from Lani Lattin Duke (Executive Director, California Confederation of the Arts)
    - Heckscher Museum, 1976, 1977, 1980, 1987,1988 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Correspondents include: Barbara Coller (guest curator for exhibition), Christopher B. Crosman (Director) re Wayne lending to exhibition, "The Artist's Mother: Portraits and Homages", (1987 November 14-1988 January 3, and The National Portrait Gallery, 1988 April 1-June 5); also includes loan agreement forms.
    - Women's International Center, 1987-1989, 1993, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Correspondents include: Gloria Lane (founder, President, Women's International Center, San Diego, CA) re Living Legacy Award; fundraising for Designated SAFE Fund.
    - Women's International Center, 1987-1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Living Legacy Awards Program (Hotel del Coronado, 1987 March 7); Correspondents include: Antoinette Fouque re Wayne's friend, Nancy Reeves; Gloria Lane (founder, President, Women's International Center, San Diego, CA) re Living Legacy Award; Communiqué newsletter of the Women's International Center (1988 January)
    - Rockwell International, 1985, 1988, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Correspondents include: Ed Longarini re Wayne submitting slides of her work for possible acquisition by Rockwell; discussion of Rockwell pursuing corporate art collection focusing on space subjects; map and directions to Rockwell's Seal Beach location; layout of the Strategic Defense Center building.
    - Rockwell International Re: Bid Raw Materials, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Business card of E.C. "Ed" Longarini (manager, Facilities Services, Rockwell International Corporation, El Segundo, CA); price quotes, layout illustrations, and installation instructions for a selection of Wayne's lithographs and paintings.
    - Women For:, 1980, 1983, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      Correspondents include: Georgia Mercer and Marilyn Kizziah (coordinators) re Wayne's proposal of auctioning a visit to her studio for the National Women's Campaign Fund fund-raising event; invitations to Women For: Women of Achievement Awards Luncheons (1980 August 26, and 1985 September 11); also includes Wayne's certificate, "In Celebration of Women's Equality Day" (1980 August 26.)
    - RO Miscellaneous, 1975, 1976, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      Correspondents include: Joseph Rothman (former special Assistant Attorney General, New York) to Dr. Andrew Robison (Curator of Graphic Arts, National Gallery of Art, Washington D.C.) and Anne Stele Marsh (President, Society of American Graphic Artists, i.e. SAGA) re SAGAS's and the Print Council of America's definition of "original print" and legislation on limited editions; Marsha Melnick and Susan E. Meyer re establishment of Roundtable Press Inc., New York (1981 April 6.)
    - Rockwell International, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Correspondents include: Ed Longarini (manager, Facilities Services, Rockwell International Corporation, El Segundo, CA) re price quotes No. 1 through 6, layout illustrations, and installation instructions for a selection of Wayne's lithographs, paintings and tapestries; also includes 35mm Kodachrome slides of Wayne's "Lemmings Day " tapestry, wall color sample paint chips, exhibition catalogue "June Wayne: Tapisseries Lithographies 1978-1980", 35mm color negatives of various works, photocopies of articles about Wayne and her work.
    - Rockwell International, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Correspondents include: Ed Longarini (manager, Facilities Services, Rockwell International Corporation, El Segundo, CA) re price quotes No. 1 through 8, layout illustrations, and installation instructions for a selection of Wayne's lithographs, paintings and tapestries; also includes exhibition announcement for Wayne's "My Palomar" lithograph series (1985 April 18-June 15, Galerie des Femmes, Paris) with reviews by Merle Schipper and others; photocopy of Louise Lewis' PrintNews article, "June Wayne's Investigations of Time"; photocopies of articles about Wayne and her work.
    - Rockwell International, 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 11)
      Correspondents include: Patti F. Mancini (Vice President, External Affairs & Communications, North American Space Operations, Rockwell International Corporation, Downey, CA) re biographies on Rockwell vice presidents, George Jeffs and George Merrick; E.C. Longarini (manager, Support Services, Rockwell International) re Wayne's proposals and quotes; business card for Marinus Welman, Fine Art (Fullerton, CA.)
    - Women in Business, 1982-1984 -1987 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Includes Women in Business (WIB) rosters (1985-1986; 1987); WIB announcement of Convention '86 with brief description of Wayne's current activities; correspondents include: Ceciley Bachnik; Laura Shields; Julie Bornstein (president, WIB) re Wayne's award and request for biographical information and photograph; Rebekah Verdon (honoree chair) and Ann Luke (president, WIB) re 10th Anniversary Dinner (1984 December 1) and Wayne's award as "Woman of the Decade"; Sandy Grant re photos of Wayne; Marilyn Miller (program chair, WIB) re Wayne's speech for anniversary party; Sunny Bernstein (public relations) re Wayne's WIB presentation (1986 June 16); Catherine Wagner; Phyllis E. Manger (Vice President, Shearson Lehman, Hutton, Beverly Hills, CA.)
    - Women In Business, 1982-1989 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      WIB membership, dinner and conference materials; "Contact" WIB newsletter (1983 June, July; 1984 May, June.)
    - Isolde, Ann, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Correspondence re Southern California Women's Caucus for Art Equity Committee's Survey of Southern California Museums and Community Galleries; Ann Isolde (Co-chair, Equity in the Arts Committee) re request for Wayne's Sex Differential in Art Exhibition Reviews"; includes draft of "Museum Policies: Equity for Women and People of Color" (M. Adams, 4/94.)
    - Walker Art Center, 1981, 1984, 1986, 1988, 1989, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Correspondents include: Carolyn Clark DeCato (registrar, Walker Art Center, Minneapolis, MN) re questionnaire for conservation program; Mary Mancuso re "The Art of June Wayne"; Elizabeth Armstrong (assistant curator) re Grunwald and Tyler Graphics catalogues, Judith Goldman essay on Tyler Graphics, including copy with Wayne's edits; Diana Gaston (curatorial intern) re slides of Tamarind Lithography Workshop for print exhibition, "First Impressions"; FAX to Walker Art Center registrar re edition of Wayne's "Adam Tempted and Eve Waiting."
    - Ocean Works, 1980-1983 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Correspondents include: Conrad Schwable (master printer) and Steve Andrews (director) re: Wayne visiting Ocean Works studio; acquiring lithography stones; opening of Wayne's "Dorothy Series" at UCLA (1982 April 4); Alexandra Yakutis (publications) re request for brief appointment; also includes two 8 x 10 inch black and white photographs of Conrad and Steve in Ocean Works studio.
    - Odoroff, Minnie, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      Correspondence re Odoroff's qualifications and charges for appraising 50 prints and one painting being donated by Wayne to the National Museum of American Art, Washington, D.C.
    - Oregon Art Institute, 1988, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Correspondents include: Gordon W. Gilkey (curator, prints and drawings) re: Wayne's "Djuna Set" catalog; letter sent to congressmen requesting support for the National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) and National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH.)
    - Printworld, 1989, 1990, 1992, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      Correspondents include: Selma Smith (editor) re inclusion and corrections for Wayne's lithograph entries in Printworld Directory, 6th and 7th editions.
    - Printworld, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Documentation forms for Wayne's lithograph entries in Printworld Directory 1987/1988.
    - Printworld, 1981, 1988-1990 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Women's Caucus for Art 1983-85 (W.C.A.)., 1984, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      Correspondents include: Carol H. Neiman (President) re membership roster and officer election proxy, and visit to Wayne's studio during 1985 annual conference; Ilee Kaplan (Fundraising Committee Chair) re 13th Annual National Conference in conjunction with the College Art Association (CAA), (February, 1985, Los Angeles); also includes WCA membership directory 1984-1985.
    - Women's Caucus for Art, 1983-1985 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Correspondents include: Eleanor Dickinson re identifying Wayne's prints; Ofelia Garcia (President) re Wayne's selection as recipient of WCA's Honor Award for Professional Achievement in the Visual Arts, 1985; also includes membership roster, 1983 and issue of WCA's newsmagazine, "Hue Points", vol. XII, no. 1 and 2, spring/summer 1983.
    - Women's Caucus for Art, 1978, 1982, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Correspondents include: Burt Pines (City Attorney, Los Angeles) re taxation and women's civil rights issues; Carol H. Neiman (Liaison from SC/WCA to Arts Coalition for Equality, aka "ACE") and Rita Starpattern (Vice President for Programs and Goals, CWAO) re Coalition of Women's Art Organizations (CWAO) 1983 Philadelphia conference panel discussion; Ellouise Schoettler Artists Equity and attending WCA conference; Ofelia Garcia (Director, The Print Club) re submitting Wayne's print for WCA conference exhibition; Linda Cunningham (Department of Art, Franklin and Marshall College, Lancaster, PA) re conference panel; Gayle Vernon re meeting at conference; WCA National Advisory Board meeting agenda (1983 February 5); WCA Fundraising Committee member roster and meeting announcement; also included is WCA National Conference program (1983 February 15-18, Philadelphia, PA.)
    - Women's Caucus for Art, 1986, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 14)